<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning to the Parliament of England. A discovery of the ends and designes of the Popish partie both abroad, and at home, in the raising and fomenting our late war, and still-continuing troubles : in an oration made to the generall Assembly of the French clergy in Paris, / by Monsieur Jaques du Perron Bishop of Angolesme, and Grand Almosner to the Queen of England. Translated out of a manuscript copy, obtained from a good hand in France, and now published for the opening their eyes that hate not the truth, and that desire to be thankfull for such a discovery. And for caution to those, to whom the Divine Providence hath intrusted the transaction of affaires, that they may most accurately take heed there be a sound foundation laid, of the so generally longed-for peace of the kingdome.</title>
            <title>Discours fait de la part de la reyne d'Angleterre. English</title>
            <author>Duperron, Jacques Davy, d. 1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E410_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204452</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863942</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863942</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116160</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81851)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116160)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 65:E410[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning to the Parliament of England. A discovery of the ends and designes of the Popish partie both abroad, and at home, in the raising and fomenting our late war, and still-continuing troubles : in an oration made to the generall Assembly of the French clergy in Paris, / by Monsieur Jaques du Perron Bishop of Angolesme, and Grand Almosner to the Queen of England. Translated out of a manuscript copy, obtained from a good hand in France, and now published for the opening their eyes that hate not the truth, and that desire to be thankfull for such a discovery. And for caution to those, to whom the Divine Providence hath intrusted the transaction of affaires, that they may most accurately take heed there be a sound foundation laid, of the so generally longed-for peace of the kingdome.</title>
                  <title>Discours fait de la part de la reyne d'Angleterre. English</title>
                  <author>Duperron, Jacques Davy, d. 1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Discours fait de la part de la reyne d'Angleterre.</note>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed to Jacques Davy Du Perron, 1556-1618, the Cardinal. The actual author was was his nephew, who was successively Bishop of Angoulême and of Evreux.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber. [i.e. October] 7th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil war, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116160:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WARNING TO THE PARLIAMENT OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcovery of the ends and deſignes of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Partie both abroad, and at home, in the raiſing and fomenting our late War, and ſtill-continuing troubles: In an ORATION made to the generall Aſſembly of the <hi>French</hi> Clergy in <hi>Paris,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Monſieur <hi>Jaques du Perron</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Angoleſme,</hi> and Grand Almoſner to the Queen of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of a Manuſcript Copy, obtained from a good hand in <hi>France,</hi> and now publiſhed for the opening their eyes that hate not the Truth, and that deſire to be thankfull for ſuch a DISCOVERY.</p>
            <p>And for Caution to thoſe, to whom the Divine Providence hath intruſted the tranſaction of Affaires, that they may moſt accurately take heed there be a ſound foundation laid, of the ſo Generally longed-for Peace of the KINGDOME.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sed ſi populus iſte vult decipi decipiatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>London Printed for <hi>R.W.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116160:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116160:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe made on the behalf of the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> in the Generall Aſſembly of the Clergy at <hi>Paris,</hi> concerning the preſent Affaires of the <hi>Catholike,</hi> Religion in the Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> By Monſieur <hi>Jaques du Perron</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Angoleſme,</hi> Grand <hi>Almoſner</hi> to Her Majeſty.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the King of Great <hi>Britain</hi> be conſtrained by the neceſſity and exigency of his Affaires, to come to an Accommodation with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled Subjects, as he will at laſt be inforced, and that in a very ſhort time, if He receive not ſpeedy and effectuall ſuccors, That Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation will neceſſarily bring with it, the totall deſtruction of the Catholike Religion in that Kingdom. For as the firſt and principall Pretext, which the Parliamentarians ſerve themſelves off, to dreſſe and colour over their Rebellion withall, and to Animate, Arme, and Unite all the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects together againſt their Lawfull Soveraign, hath been, to make them believe that he was a Catholike, and that he would introduce, and bring the Catholike Religion into that Kingdom; And as the firſt Article of all the Treaties that have been ſet on foot, and put forward by them hitherto, hath alwaies been, that of the Ruine and Extermination of the Catholikes; it is not to be doubted, they will never conclude any Accord or Agreement with their Prince, but upon that rigorous Condition, that the little Catholiciſme that yet remaines there, ſhould for ever be Baniſhed from thence, and that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116160:3"/>all the Arms and Forces of England and Scotland ſhall be joyned together (as they have long ſince reſolved amongſt themſelves, and publiſhed in Print) to execute this unhappy and wicked deſign plainly, that is to Maſſacre and cut the throats of all the poor Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, as they have already begun to do in divers places; And to drown and extinguiſh for ever in their blood, the Remainders and reliques of Religion, not only in England and Scotland, but alſo in Ireland, where they have been almoſt all preſerved in the Orthodox belief, notwithſtanding all the perſecutions that have been raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them for theſe hundred years laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>Now the deſtruction of Monarchy in England, and the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Republike, and eſpecially of a Puritane Republike, which is the end that the Parliamentarians aime at, carrieth with it the greateſt prejudice that may be to the Catholike Religion: for the Extent of it will not be only in England, in Scotland, or in Ireland, but in all other parts of Chriſtendome. For if this Popular and Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane State, ſhall once be formed in theſe three great Kingdoms, and after that ſhall Unite it ſelf with the Hereticks of <hi>Germany, Holland,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as is moſt agreeable to all Maximes of State, Religion, and Intereſt, and w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> to effect, they are eſpecially concerned, and which is a deſign, which the Parliamentarians had formed in their mindes from the inſtant of their Revolt, and of which they now ſpare not to make a clear and open profeſſion: All theſe powers thus United by the Intereſts of State, and of Religion, the moſt ſtrict and ſacred bonds of humane ſociety, will render themſelves ſo formidable to all the reſt of Chriſtendome, as they will be able in ſucceſſion of time (if God ſhall not mightily interpoſe his hand) to undermine, and utterly to ruine all the Catholikes. And this is that which the Parliamentarians hope to come unto at laſt, when they ſhall have rooted up Monarchy from among themſelves, for they hate the Church, yet more then they hate Royalty. And is it not to be feared, that if the Catholikes of other Countreys, ſhall ſhew themſelves ſo little ſenſible of the ruine of Religion in England, and ſhall not be ready to give their aſſiſtance for the maintenance and preſervation of the ſame, that God by his juſt judgement ſhould permit that themſelves ſhould fall into the ſame unhappineſſe and miſery of Schiſme and Hereſie, from which they have had no heart to preſerve and defend their brethren, and their neighbors? And is it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116160:3"/>not to be feared that God to puniſh our regardleſnes, &amp; looſenes in the things of his ſervice, and of his glory, and our little zeal for the Augmentation, and Conſervation of the Catholike Religion, ſhould permit the ſame Catholike Religion to be wholly ruined, and root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the reſt of thoſe Countreys, in which it yet continueth in <hi>Europe,</hi> as in the Ages paſt, to chaſtiſe the ſins of thoſe that lived before us, he hath permitted that it ſhould be wholly deſtroyed, in all <hi>Aſia, Affrick,</hi> and the greateſt part of <hi>Europe</hi> it ſelfe, and to tranſplant it wholly into <hi>America,</hi> and that new world, which were the greateſt unhappineſſe that could befall us; and which we ought to endeavour to hinder by all the meanes we can, all the dayes of our lives?</p>
            <p>The King of England hath promiſed by a Letter which he hath written to the Queen his ſpouſe, to revoke and repeal all thoſe Laws which have at any time been made againſt the Catholikes in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, in caſe he can receive from the Catholikes any aſſiſtance, to put him into a Condition of power and Authority to be able to do it. There is now no danger to declare this promiſe, which hath been kept ſecret hitherto: for that the Parliamentarians having ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed the Copie of the ſaid Letter, have Printed and publiſhed the ſame, to render the King the moſt odious to the People that they can; &amp; to render the Catholikes the moſt ſuſpects. And were not this now the greateſt good that could poſſible come to the Catholike Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? For were not this to give and eſtabliſh in a ſort, the liberty of Catholike Religion in England? which if it were once eſtabliſhed there, it is moſt certain that we ſhould ſhortly ſee the greateſt part of that Countrey re-united to the Church: for there are now already a fourth part, yea, even near a third part, who are Catholikes, either ſecret or open; There is one other third part, who are held in Schiſm, only from the apprehenſion of temporall puniſhment, and the loſſe of their goods, and by the fear of the Laws, which being once revoked, as the King of England promiſeth now they ſhall, in caſe he can be aſſiſted, they would alſo preſently embrace the Catholike faith. And who can tell whether the divine providence hath not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the King of England ſhould fall into thoſe difficulties, and extremities, into which he is now reduced, to the end, that being preſſed by the neceſſity and exigency of his Affaires, he might take this good reſolution, which God no doubt hath inſpired him with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116160:4"/>for the advantage of his Church? And who knowes whether when this King hath been ſo ſeaſonably and ſenſibly engaged and obliged by the Catholikes, God may not take that occaſion to touch his heart, and open his eyes to the light of the faith?</p>
            <p>The ſecond conſideration, which ought to carry you more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and particularly to this aſſiſtance beyond the reſt of the Church, is your particular intereſt, that is to ſay, the danger in which you are, in regard of your vicinity to England, as being neerer then any other Catholike kingdome; ſo as when Hereſie ſhall have ruined Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in England, it may with greateſt ſpeed, paſſe over to deſtroy it alſo in France.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Res tua tunc agitur, paries cum proximus ardet.</hi> For we know of certain knowledge, that this is the deſigne and ſcope of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarians; and that this is all the hope and the only refuge of the Huguenots; upon this hope it is, that they travell with ſo great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and vehemency, to help forward, and to publiſh the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Parliamentarians; 'Tis upon this hope they Contribute ſo great ſums <note n="*" place="margin"> That the Reader be not miſtaken in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, he is to take notice, that the Orator uſeth this as an Argument, to provoke the French Clergy to a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution to the Queen in Emulation of the Hugue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots; wherein he impoſeth upon them, there never ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ſo much as one peny ever leavied by them, or ſent into England, for the uſe of the Parliament.</note> which they leavy upon themſelves, and ſecretly convey into England. And truly this their hope perhaps is not ſo vaine nor ill grounded, as ſome may be ready to imagine: for if the <hi>Huguenots</hi> at their firſt birth, and when they began to appear in this Kingdome, being only upheld by the protection of ſome petty Hereticall Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> made themſelves in ſhort time ſo conſiderable, as they were able to ſet on foot at divers times ſuch Prodigious Armies, to give an hundred and an hundred encount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with our forces, to gaine many ſignall Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to take a great number of the beſt Townes of this Kingdome, to keep whole Provinces intire, and to ruine and deſtroy wherever they came the Catholike Religion, of which we ſee yet, the lamentable marks and ſcars in all parts of this Kingdome, but principally in the Dioceſes of <hi>Guienne</hi> and <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc;</hi> what will it be, when beſide the ſuccours of the Hereticks of <hi>Germany</hi> (who are now incomparably more powerfull then they were in thoſe times,) they ſhall be aſſiſted by the Puritanes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland and Ireland, united in one body of a Republike, the moſt formidable of all Chriſtendome? certainly it muſt be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116160:4"/>avowed, that all thoſe evils with which they have afflicted the Church of France in the times paſt, are nothing, in comparriſon of thoſe with which we are threatned for the future. The truth is, the <hi>Huguenots</hi> have been very much weakened, but they have not been yet intirely rooted out, they are yet in as great number, and have as great ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity againſt us as ever; we have taken indeed from them their Towns, and ſtrong places, but their hatred toward us remains, and their deſire of Revenge ſtill lives, and they attend but for an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to make the ſame appear, which can never be preſented to them more favorably, then by the eſtabliſhment of a Puritane Republike in England; and therefore, if this ſhall ever come to paſſe, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt it will come to paſſe one day, if it be not preſently and effectually hindred, we ſhall ſee again in France, the Churches ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Sepulchres profaned, the aſhes of the dead caſt into the wind, as they have done even to ſome of our Kings and others. Behold, this is that which the <hi>Huguenots</hi> of France promiſe us, this is that which the Parliamentarians of England prepare for us, in caſe they can finiſh their work with their King and their Queen. Shall it be ſaid to poſterity? Shall it be ſaid to the ſhame of Catholikes, and particularly to the oprobry of the Clergy of France, that the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenots</hi> of France contributed ſo joyfully and freely, great ſums for the aid of the Parliamentarians, that is to ſay, for the enemies of God, of the holy. Church his ſpouſe, of your dignities and ſacred Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter? ſhall it be ſaid that they have made great Collections to ſend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to England, to help to deſtroy, and root up from the foundation the Kingdom of Ieſus Chriſt, and to advance yet further, and ſet up there the Kingdome of Satan; hoping when that ſhall be effected to their mindes, to do the ſame thing here in France: and that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, and eſpecially the Eccleſiaſticks, who live only upon the Patrimony of Ieſus Chriſt, and who have proteſted in their Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the face and preſence of the whole Church, that they would renounce all the periſhable poſſeſſions of this world, and to have none other Inheritance then the Lord, no other Poſſeſſion then Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>(Dominus pars haereditatis meae &amp; calicis mei)</hi> ſhould not a little retrench and abridge themſelves in ſome ſmall thing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to help and aſſiſt the ſetting up of the Kingdome of the ſame Lord and the ſame Ieſus Chriſt in England, and to preſerve to him the Inheritance which he hath there purchaſed to himſelf, at the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116160:5"/>Price of his owne moſt pretious blood, and with that of ſo many Martyrs, and by conſequence inevitable, to preſerve unto him here in France that kingdome, which he hath here poſſeſſed for theſe ſixteen hundred years?</p>
            <p>I conclude this diſcourſe with one conſideration, which reſpects you yet more particularly then the reſt of the Church, in regard of the quality you bear as French. A Conſideration nevertheleſſe which the Queen of England hath even commanded me to ſuppreſſe, conceiving the Intereſt of her own perſon, and that of her children, of ſo ſmall conſideration, as ſhe dares not mingle them with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of Religion. Notwithſtanding it ſeemed to me, that I could not omit it without breach of Piety and good Nature that is, to conſider a little the eminent perill and danger, wherein the Queen of England and her children now are, to fall into a more deplorable and miſerable condition then ever perſons of their birth and quality were reduced unto: to ſee on the one ſide ſix young Princes and Princeſſes, the tendernes of whoſe age, is yet within the verge &amp; Limit of Innocence; Princes, which are the grand-children, Nephews, and Couſin Germans of our Kings; Princes, who derive their birth and blood from twenty or two and twenty Kings of England, and from twelve or fifteen Kings of Scotland, and who are generally allyed to all the Crowned heads of Chriſtendome, and of whom for that cauſe, it may as juſtly be ſaid, as of the children of the Emperors of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> of old, that they were ingendred of Purple,
<q>
                  <l>Cum Majeſtate creatos,</l>
                  <l>Nulla<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> privatae paſſos contagia ſortis.</l>
               </q>
Born in the glory and midſt of the ſplendor of Soveraign Majeſty; nouriſhed and brought up upon the Royall Throne, in hopes to command one day great and powerfull Nations: To ſee them I ſay now at the very point of being deſpoyled of three great Kingdomes, which ſo many of their Anceſtors have left them from hand to hand, as a well-aſſured patrimony; to be conſtrained to leave their native Countrey now in their tender Age, and to wander in ſtrange countreys as vagabonds to ſeek the ſecurity of their lives and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and even there to eat that bread, which they cannot eat in their own houſe, and amongſt their own Subjects and Citizens, is a thing, that none who hath ought of the tenderneſſe of a man left in him can ſpeak or think of without teares.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116160:5"/>
            <q>In Servitutem cadere de Regno grave eſt</q>
            <p>Was the ſaying of a deſpoyled Prince in the Tragick Poet; to ſee on the other ſide a moſt Catholike Princeſſe, whoſe veines contein and hold, and in which there runs along the pretious blood of our St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> which is not only the life of her body, but alſo animates, and impregnates her heart with the ſame ſentments of Piety, which hath acquired to that great Saint a Crown of Glory in the Heavens, &amp; a ſhrine in our Temples; A Princeſs, who in imitation of that moſt imitable Saint, hath ſet up the Altars, and the true worſhip of God in England, and hath cauſed the Catholike Religion again to grow and triumph there, with all the ſplendor and glory imaginable, for the ſpace of 15 or 16 years, in deſpite of all the oppoſition that Hereſie could make againſt it, and that after it had been continually oppreſſed and perſecuted for the ſpace of an hundred years: yea, ſo far had this proceeded, as there hath been even in the chief City of the Kingdome, a Covent of Capuchin Fathers, Preaching, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing, and Confeſſing every day publikely, and that not only in French, but alſo in Engliſh, adminiſtring the Sacraments, &amp; Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting divine ſervice w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> as much ſolemnity and liberty, &amp; I durſt even ſay in proportion, with as great affluence of people, as in any Church in <hi>Paris,</hi> The King ſaying nothing to it, nor any of the Miniſters of State, or Juſtice of that Kingdome daring to impeach or hinder it, eſpecially for theſe laſt ten years; yea, even ſo far, that there hath been ſeen to the Admiration of all Chriſtendome, that which hath not been ſeen ſince the time of the Schiſme, and that which none could have dared ever to hope to ſee again, namely, Reſidents from the Court of England at <hi>Rome,</hi> to Treat there with the Pope of the affaires of Religion, and Reciprocally three Nuntio's from the Pope in the Court of England, namely, the Seigniours, <hi>Gregory Panzani,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Mileto</hi> in Italy, <hi>Georgio Coneo,</hi> a Scottiſh man by Nation, but a Domeſtick of the laſt Pope, and of the Cardinall <hi>Barbarini,</hi> and Seignior <hi>Roſſetti,</hi> who was made Cardinall at his going out of England, all theſe Negotiating in the ſaid Court, during the ſpace of ſeven or eight years, with as much liberty, yea, even familiarity, as in the Court of any other Catholike Prince whatſoever: and all this by the conduct, zeale, and credit of the Queen of England, who by theſe ſweet ſteps walked fairely on toward the Converſion of that Kingdome, and which it ſeemed, we might ſpeedily have hoped for,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116160:6"/>after ſo happy and proſperous beginnings (but our ſins have turned away that unexpected happineſſe) a Princeſſe, who hath given a confidence to the poor Engliſh Catholikes, to come forth from their retirements, where they remained ſhut up in obſcurity, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the light with their faces erected, to profeſſe and exerciſe their Religion with all aſſurance; to aſpire after, and actually obtain Offices and Charges in the Court and State, after they had been for the ſpace of an age without liberty of breathing, or rather ſighing in ſecret; a Princeſs, who by her Alms, or rather by her immenſe Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities (of which I can give Teſtimonie, for that the moſt part thereof paſſed through my hands,) hath reſtored life to many intire families, (yea, even of the moſt Noble of England) who had been deſpoyled of all their Eſtates for the cauſe of Religion, &amp; who were upon the point to die by a cruell and lingring famine; yet notwithſtanding, we may ſee at this day this Princeſſe (of ſo excellent merit, and who hath ſo deeply obliged all Catholikes) hath been twice chaſed from her own Kingdome, and forced to flie from the cruelty of her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies with infinite labour and perill, and that within 14 dayes after her delivery of a childe, who not content to have proſecuted her criminally, and to death, in their Parliament, by their devilliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies they have perſecuted her in this her flight, purſuing her both by ſea and land, with Cannon diſcharged, (one ſhot of which came into her ſhip) thinking to interrupt the courſe of her flight, and to make her fall into the hands of her enemies, who followed her at the diſtance of muſquet ſhot, other ſhot being made againſt a little houſe where ſhe was retired, entring the Chamber of her Lady of Honour, and of her maids of Honour, and killed ſome perſons of her train; ſo as this poor Princeſſe was forced for the ſaving of her life, with all ſpeed to riſe and flie 5 or 600 paces thence, without having the leiſure to put on her clothes, and this on foot, being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in night, and in the deep of Winter, in the midſt of ſnow and froſt, (it being in the month of <hi>February</hi>) and to go hide her ſelf in a ditch, and behind a little riſing ground, to put her ſelf under that ſhelter from the Cannon, which continually played for the ſpace of two whole houres, the bullets flying over her head, and falling down at the feet of her Majeſty, the Rebels having no reſpect either to her perſon, or yet to her ſex, which hath alwaies found commiſeration &amp; pity in the moſt wilde and ſavage ſpirits, nor yet regarding her long
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116160:6"/>ſickneſſe, which had brought her even within two fingers of death; neither yet the Royall Character which ſhe bears, which hath been wont to finde Veneration among Subjects, even the moſt revolted; nor the blood of France of which ſhe is deſcended, and which is now redoubted and reverenced throughout the world; to ſee her now deprived of that, which of all things in the world (on this ſide God) is moſt dear unto her, namely, the King her husband, and the Princes her children, and that which Augments her troubles &amp; anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, even to infinite, is the continuall apprehenſions and fear in which ſhe is, leſt the chance of war ſhould cauſe them to fall into the hands of their enemies, who no doubt would forthwith imbrue their ſacrilegious hands in the Royall bloud; to ſee her at the very point now, in the flower of her age, about 35 or 36 years, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced (ſhe and all her family) into a prodigious calamity, into which ſhee had been already fallen, as to her own perſon, had it not been hindred by the charity that hath been extended to her by the King and Queen. Laſtly, to ſee this Princeſſe ſuffer all this for the moſt juſt cauſe in the World, and that which hath made all our Saints and Martyrs, that is to ſay, for that ſhe is a Catholike, and re-eſtabliſhed, and made to flouriſh again the Catholike Religion in England: behold this is all her Crime, in the opinion of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentarians, this the only fault of which they can convince her, and of which they have declared her guilty by all their Printed Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, after they had with greateſt malice and diligence made a more accurate ſear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n into her whole life, then into the life of the moſt wicked Malefactor, even of thoſe who are guilty of treaſon it ſelf. And this ſeems to me to be a motive that ſhould ſo much more excite us to Contribution in this cauſe, for that it depends upon us for ſuccour and relief. It is not without the greateſt regret, and with very much unwillingneſſe and ſhame, that ſhee is brought to this point to ask and importune your aide: but her own Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and the whole Catholike cauſe, eſpecially in England, are at preſent come to that State, that ſhe believed it was her duty on this occaſion, even to offer ſome violence to her own diſpoſition, to overcome the greatneſſe of her ſpirit, and to put out, and lay by, all ſenſe of that ſhame, confuſion, and repugnancie, which hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deterred her.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:116160:7"/>
            <q>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> turpe putat quid quid miſeros fortuna jubet.</q>
            <p>She knows your hearts ſo filled and flaming with the zeale of the Catholike Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhe knows that you are ſo deeply affectionate to the Royall blood of our Kings, ſhe knows you ſo Chriſtian-like charitable, and tenderly compaſſionate to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of all afflicted, even thoſe of loweſt quality and condition, how much mote then of Crowned heads (whereof her ſelf is one) caſt down into, and overwhelmed in the Abyſſe, &amp; bottom of all manner of miſery &amp; unhappines, that ſhe believes it cannot be a thing unacceptable to offer you this an occaſion, (the moſt glorious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, and moſt meritorious before God) to give to all Chriſtendome a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Demonſtration, that theſe good and laudable diſpoſitions do dwell and worke in you. For how can you ever better imploy your Liberality and your Alms, then to hinder the progreſſe of Hereſie, to advance Religion, and to retire out of a totall ruine all the Catholikes of England? to deliver from miſery, from almes &amp; from beggery it ſelf (I make no difficulty to uſe theſe tearms, for that the Queen of England hath held it no diſhonour to uſe them, and to write them with her own hand in the memoriall which ſhee gave me of thoſe things, which I ſhould repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto you on her part) to deliver therefore I ſay, from almes and beggery, a Queen, and Princes who are the children of thoſe who have founded and endowed our benefices, and who have beſtowed them upon us?</p>
            <p>The aſſiſtance which the Queen of England deſires of you, is, what in your own prudence you think fit, both for the ſums you ſhall lend, and of the manner of furniſhing thereof, whether at one intire paiment, or at divers, as being deſirous to be as little but then ſome to the Clergie as ſhee can: which alſo ſhee deſires not in free and pure gift, but only by way of Loan, and that only untill God ſhall pleaſe to reſtore her affaires into ſome better eſtate. This, if you ſhall do, you will have a great part of the glory of the happy re-eſtabliſhment of the Catholike Religion and of Monarchy in the Kingdome of England, you ſhall be the cauſe of the ſalvation ſpirituall and temporall of an infinite number of perſons, who now ſtretch forth their hands unto you out of the midſt of their perils, and from the darkneſſe of their priſons, imploring your aſſiſtance, as doth alſo all the remainder of the poor Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church in England, no more now triumphant as I have ſometimes ſeen it, no more ſimply militant, but if I may ſo ſay, ſuffering, perſecuted, expiring &amp; dying, which implore your aſſiſtance by the mouth of their Queen, and by me: And who by their prayers and teares, and it may be alſo by their blood, (if God ſhall give them grace to conſummate their Martyrdome by the loſſe of their lives) will draw down upon you the benedictions of heaven, and will cauſe you to merit immortall praiſes among men, and a crown of glory to Eternity.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>This Speech was made <date>the 19 of <hi>February,</hi> 46.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
